{
  "reference_number": "11083",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "It may be necessary to bring that date forward - climate change accelerates, international cooperation requires faster action,\n technology innovation, global catastrophe - war financial collapse, oil collapse"
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": "CO2 is cumulative, we cannot continue to add more, Methane is not cumulative, about 11 year turnover, but far more serious\n warming effect and if stabilised at current level will still have dangerous climate change effect. The Climate Commission must address\n\n the level of stabilisation of methane at the lowest possible level as one of its first actions. Reduction of numbers of cattle is essential.\n This can be addressed by supporting farmers to switch to regenerative and organic farming, This will mean lower inputs of fertiliser\n which has the additional benefit of reducing N2O emissions and cleaner rivers. Also reduce imports of supplementary feed like palm\n\n kernal. Lower inputs means costs are reduced so farmers' profits still OK. New Zealand needs to have a strategy to move away from\n intensive dairying to alternative land use. Methane escape from oil and gas industry can only be addressed by stopping fracking and\n stopping eploration fromoil and gas. Reducing methane is extrememly urgent."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "International carbon credits transfer NZ emissions to another country. There are no guarantees that ICs are environmentally reliable.\n\n Reductions can be achieved by: -move away from fossil fuels, 100% renewable electricity, EVs, Electric public transport, stricter\n building codes for the best practice insulation and passive heating, reduced road haulage, strong local economies, -\n\n resilientcommunities (more self reliant for food and manufactured goods),. Carbon sequestration - more planting of trees native\n permanent effect, also build soil carbon and biochar. These changes may reduce GDP as compared with the current Business as\n Usual model. However the economic studies mentioned in the document have failed to highlight the cost of doing nothing. Already\n\n different parts of the country are experiencing large economic costs from flooding and erosion, while Pacific Island nations are being\n turned into climate change migrants. Failure to reduce carbon emissions will cause severe weather events and metres of sea level\n\n rise which will flood coastal cities permanently. This would be an economic cost much greater than that predicted from reducing\n emissions."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The current level of carbon equivalents already in the atmosphere will continue to have a warming effect for the indefinite future. We\n\n actually have to remove CO2 from the atmosphere eventually. The only change to the 2050 target might be to bring it forward as\n some European companies have done of we are not making sufficient progress on reductions."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Planning 15 years ahead is what we should always be doing. ut breaking it into 5 year bands focuses us on what we have to achieve."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "Transitioning from one 15 year block to the next could be made easier by making the last 5 year block a bridge to the next 15 year\n\nblock."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "How do we define exceptional circumstances. It is important the Government does not become diverted from the reduction targets\nby its electoral agenda and giving freedom to change the second 5 year target could divert the focus. There is a temptation to say\n\nbecause New Zealand is a small player we can rest on our laurels but it is vital we remain committed to the international cooperative\neffort. Exceptional circumstances could only be international catastrophe, such as war, or a major natural disaster such as an\nearthquake."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Setting the targets must be carefully managed in the social, economic and fiscal context of the time with commitment to honouring\n\nthe Treaty of Waitangi. We can reduce emissions while ensuring a just and inclusive society, an economy that focuses on wellbeing\nfor all and restoration of ecosystems. However reducing carbon emissions is urgent and the consequence of worsening climate\n\nchange will damage the economy and cause social disruption and hardship for the poorest in society so reducing emissions is a\npriority."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "A timeframe of about 6 months will allow time for consultation."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "This question seems to overlap with Q8. In the past an overriding issue of government policy has been GDP. It seems likely that the\nfuture of oil is very uncertain and we will struggle to remain within planetary boundaries both for resources and for sinks. It seems the\n\neconomic pie will be reduced whether we reduce emissions or allow climate change to wreak havoc on the planet. Those citizens\nwho have enjoyed a very high standard of living for the last 50 years may experience a drop in their standard of living and put\npressure on the government to compromise on the emissions target.. That is why the Government needs to have legislation in place\n\nwhich keeps it focussed on reducing emissions while being committed to the wellbeing of all citizens especially the poorest, and\nwhile honouring its obligations to Maori under the Treaty of Waitangi. The government also needs to work within the international\n\ncommunity through the UNFCCC, ensuring cooperation amongst nation states."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "There is some similarity here to the position of the Parliamentary Commissioner for the Environment but on a much bigger scale. The\nCCC will be independent with a very wide range of expertise and must advise the Government based on the best science and\n\nmonitor how the Government is taking heed of this advice. But for the first time in our history the health of the planet must take\npriority and if Government fails to heed the Commission's advice the consequences could be catastrophic."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "Carbon emissions are not an externality but are a part of the ecosystem and so affect biological processes. Putting a price on carbon\naims to modify society's carbon emissions. The Government should control the price of carbon. An ETS allows the market to\n\ndetermine the price of carbon and the government will have to try and control that through determining the number of units available.\nHowever the financial world may finally be recognising that markets are not infallible. A carbon tax and dividend may still be a better\nalternative to the ETS."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Adaptation to climate change mainly happens at the local government level. This is a major exercise and cost and Central\n\ngovernment must work with local government both by using money from the ETS to support local government and by assisting with\nplanning. Central government also needs to work with Insurance companies to assist private householders who are at risk from sea\n\nlevel rise, flooding and other climate change effects. It may be necessary to set up a fund similar to the earthquake commission to\nmanage insurance claims from climate change effects."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I support the preparation of a national climate risk assessment, a national policy plan to address those risks identified and a\n\nmonitoring and reporting framework."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Please note I started an earlier submission and could not recover it. Please regard this one as my substantive submission. I also\nresponded to a Gen Zero online document."
    }
  ]
}
